A Guide to the Ute Westrom Architectural Papers, 1968-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ute Westrom Architectural Papers, 1968-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1996-023
2 boxes, 1 tube box, 2 oversized folders; 1.4 cu. ft.
Ute Westrom was born in 1939 in Berlin, Germany, the oldest of four children of architect Hilde Westrom. In 1968 she earned an architect's diploma from the Technical University of Berlin. She is a practicing architect in Berlin and an active member of the International Union of Women Architects (UIFA.) Her collection includes information about the restoration of the Martin Gropius Bau in Berlin and the Sozialkasse des Berliner Baugewerbes in Berlin, both designed by Westrom and her husband and partner Winnetou Kampmann. The collection also contains photos and drawings for other projects, her vita, and material presented at UIFA congresses in the 1970s.
Ute Westrom
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Ute Westrom Architectural Papers were donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture at the Special Collections in 1996 by their creator. Additions to the collection were given in 2000, 2002 and 2005.
Biographical Information
Ute Westrom was born in 1939 in Berlin, Germany. She was oldest of four children of Hilde Westrom, a well-known early woman architect. In 1959, Ute Westrom studied psychology, philosophy, and sociology at the University of Hamburg. In the same year, she began her study of architecture at the Technical University of Berlin. While a student, Westrom worked for an architect in Lubeck, Germany in 1962, for the municipal planning office in Paris in 1963, and toured North Africa and the Middle East. She graduated in 1968 with an architect's diploma from the Technical University of Berlin.
Between 1972 and 1984, Westrom was involved with the design and construction of at least 320 apartments throughout Berlin, primarily for a low-income, municipal housing project funded by the Railway Building Association. During this period, she also designed individual houses, furnishings, and won various design competitions.
From 1977 through 1984, Westrom became increasingly involved with the conversion of old buildings for new uses, many as museums. In the process, she designed and implemented new forms of lighting, furnishings, display cases and panels for organizations such as the Berlin Hall of Fine Arts, the Berlin Gallery, and the Brohan Museum. Of particular importance was her collaboration with partner and husband Winnetou Kampmann in the reconstruction of the former Museum of Applied Arts, built in the late nineteenth-century by Martin Gropius and known as the Martin-Gropius-Bau, into an international art center. The restoration of the 1877 landmark was necessary after it was destroyed during in an air raid during World War II. Another notable project was her original design for a new office building for the Sozialkasse des Berliner Baugewerbes in Berlin. Westrom continues to be active in designing office buildings, town planning projects, museum expansions, and condominiums throughout Berlin.
Scope and Content
The Ute Westrom Architectural Papers include many original drawings and photographs showing her architectural work, as well as some materials from the meetings of L'Union Internationale des Femmes Architects (UIFA).
The collection contains various versions of Westrom's curriculum vitae and incomplete lists of projects she has worked on in both German and English. There are also copies of papers presented at the Third and Fourth International Congresses of UIFA, with additional materials on presenters at the fourth congress. UIFA materials are mostly in French and English.
Architectural project materials include selected original drawings from many projects, small printed versions of drawings, photographs of completed buildings, and some descriptive text about the projects. Descriptive texts and articles may be in German, English, or both languages. All of the projects are located in Berlin, Germany. The information in the collection is generally final drafts of drawings and photographs of completed projects from near the completion date.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by grouping together biographical data, UIFA congress materials, and project materials. All material is arranged in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Another collection of Ute Westrom's papers is housed at the Berlinische Galerie in Berlin, Germany.
Separated Material
The following items were transferred to the Special Collections Rare Book room:
Kampmann, Winnetou, Ute Westrom, and Hans-Joachim Arndt. Martin-Gropius-Bau: die Geschichte seiner Wiederherstellung. New York: Prestel, 1999. Call number NA6750.B44 M377 1999
Contents List
- BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION
  - Professional vitae and project lists, 1968-2005 (Box-folder 1:1)
- UIFA INFORMATION
  - UIFA 3rd Congress at Bucharest, Romania, 1972
    - Papers presented at conference (Box-folder 1:2)
  - UIFA 4th Congress at Ramsar/Teheran, Iran, 1976
    - Notes on conference (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Biographies of conference presenters (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Papers presented at conference (Box-folder 1:6)
- PROJECTS
  - Furstenbrunnerweg 91-101, Umbau Burogebaude (Office building renovation), 1969-1970
    - One drawing (Box 3)
  - Mobel (Built-in furniture, various locations), 1970, n.d.
    - Three drawings (Oversize 1)
  - Delbruck Strasse 8, Kindertagesstatte Judische Gemeinde, (Kindergarten for a Jewish Congregation), 1970-1971
    - Two drawings (Box 3)
  - Brinkmann Strasse, Wohnanlage Sozialer Wohnungsbau (Housing project, 127 publicly financed apartments), 1972-1973
    - One drawing (Oversize 1)
  - Quermatenweg 5-7, Wohnanlage Eigentumswohnungen (Housing project, 11 condominiums), 1973-1975
    - Photos (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Four drawings (Oversize 1)
  - Homburger Strasse, Wohnanlage Sozialer Wohnungsbau (Housing project, 115 publicly financed apartments and garden area), 1974-1975
    - Photos (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Three drawings, one color poster (Oversize 1)
  - Budapester Strasse, Kunsthalle Berlin (Berlin Hall of Fine Arts renovation), 1976-1977
    - Photos (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Two drawings (Oversize 1)
  - Ahrweiler Strasse, Wohnanlage Sozialer Wohnungsbau, (Housing project, publicly financed apartments and garden area), 1976-1981
    - Photos (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Two drawings (Box 3)
    - Two drawings, one photo (Oversize 1)
  - Niederkirchner Strasse 7, Martin-Gropius-Bau (Reconstruction and renovation of the former Museum of Applied Arts known as the Martin Gropius building), 1977-1986, 1991
    - Photos (Box-folder 1:11)
    - Publication and brochures (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Eight drawings, one photo (Oversize 1)
  - Krumme Strasse, Studentenwohnheim (Student dormitory), 1978-1979
    - Drawings (Box-folder 1:13)
    - One drawing (Oversize 1)
  - Jeben Strasse 2, Berlinsche Galerie (Reconstruction and furnishings for the Berlin Gallery - State Museum for Modern Art, Photography, and Architecture), 1978-1979
    - Plans, photos, and article (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Eight drawings (Oversize 2)
  - Kommunikative Wohnbebauung fur Wissenschaftler - Wettbewerb (Social and residential community for scientists - Competition entry), 1981-1982
    - Project description (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Two drawings (Oversize 2)
  - Alt-Lankwitz 23-29, Wohnanlage sozialer Wohnungsbau, (Housing Project, publicly financed apartments and garden area), 1982-1985
    - Project description and photos (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Six drawings, four color renderings (Oversize 2)
  - Hamburger Bahnhof (Hamburg train station), 1984-1989
    - Article (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Strasse der 17. Juni, Ernst-Reuter-Haus Seminar- und Tagungsraume (Ernst Reuter House renovation as classroom and meeting space for the Center for the Institute of Town Planning), 1985-1988
    - Project description and photos (Box-folder 1:18)
    - Three drawings (Oversize 2)
  - Erweiterung Berlin Museum - Wettbewerb (Expansion of the Berlin Museum - Competition entry), 1988-1989
    - One drawing (Oversize 2)
  - Schloss Strasse 1, Brohan-Museum, (Expansion of the Brohan Museum for Art Deco), 1988-1991
    - Photos (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Magazine article on project[Bauwelt 1991 Heft 28], 1991/07/26 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - One drawing (Box 3)
    - Four drawings (Oversize 2)
  - Molkenmarkt 1-3, Palais Schewerin, (Redevelopment of building as offices for the Berlin government), 1992-1993
    - One drawing (Oversize 2)
  - Luckstrasse 72-73, Sozialkasse des Berliner Baugewerbes (New office building for the welfare fund of the Berlin building industry), 1991-1995
    - Project description and plans (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Invitation to opening and photos (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Publications with articles about the Sozialkasse Burogebaude (Box-folder 2:4)
    - One drawing (Box 3)
    - Thirteen drawings, two hand-colored elevations (Oversize 2)
  - Reconstruction des 1904 Versicherungsgebaude von A. Messel (Reconstruction of the 1904 insurance building by A. Messel), 1994-1996
    - Project description (Box-folder 2:5)